Guide to the David and Esther Smith Papers TAM 731
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
David and Esther Smith Papers
1941-2006
1941-1958
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Smith, David
Smith, Esther
Smith, Karen
TAM 731
2.5 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes.
David Smith was a union organizer in Cleveland, Ohio for the Cleveland Industrial Union Council in 1941. He began naval training as an Aviation Machinist at the Ford Navy Service School in Dearborn Michigan in 1942, but was held by Naval Intelligence after graduation due to suspected subversive activity before advancing to full naval service from 1942 to 1945. Esther Smith (nee Frank) served as Executive Secretary to the Town and Village Tenants' Committee to End Discrimination in Stuyvesant Town, and fought against the attempted eviction of anti-discrimination activists from Stuyvesant Town by the corporate landlord, Metropolitan Life Insurance Agency. This collection consists of letters from 1941 to 1945 from David to Esther documenting his organizing activities; his service in the United States Navy during World War II; David and Esther's early relationship and marriage; and the circumstances in which David was suspected of subversive activity by Naval Intelligence. The collection also includes materials concerning anti-discrmination in housing, illegal evictions, and efforts to desegregate Stuyvesant Town from 1949 to 1958, including documents from the Town and Village Tenants' Committee to End Discrimination in Stuyvesant Town.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Karen Smith in 2017. The accession number associated with this gift is 2017.055.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
David Smith was a union organizer in Cleveland, Ohio for the Cleveland Industrial Union Council in 1941. He began naval training as an Aviation Machinist at the Ford Navy Service School in Dearborn Michigan in 1942, but was held by Naval Intelligence after graduation due to suspected subversive activity before advancing to full naval service from 1942 to 1945. In 1945 David Smith married Esther Frank after writing to her extensively during his three years of naval service.
Esther Smith (nee Frank), of the Bronx, New York served as Executive Secretary to the Town and Village Tenants' Committee to End Discrimination in Stuyvesant Town, and fought against the attempted eviction of anti-discrimination activists from Stuyvesant Town by the corporate landlord, Metropolitan Life Insurance Agency.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of letters from 1941 to 1945 from David Smith to Esther Smith (nee Frank). They document David Smith's activities as an organizer in the United Electrical Workers in Cleveland, Ohio; his service in the United States Navy during World War II; and David and Esther's early relationship and marriage. This correspondence also documents the circumstances in which David was suspected of subversive activity by Naval Intelligence in between basic training and his naval service. There are also Communist Party USA (CPUSA) documents and pamphlets, as well as materials concerning anti-discrmination in housing, illegal evictions, and efforts to desegregate Stuyvesant Town from 1949 to 1958, including documents from the Town and Village Tenants' Committee to End Discrimination in Stuyvesant Town.
Race discrimination.; Discrimination in housing -- New York (N.Y.); Activist to activist; World War, 1939-1945.; Correspondence.; Civil rights workers.; Political activists -- United States.; Stuyvesant Town (New York, N.Y.); Cleveland Industrial Union Council (Cleveland, Ohio); United States. Department of the Navy; Smith, Karen
- Correspondence, 1941-09-1943-08 (Box 1, Folder 1-10)
- Correspondence, 1943-09-1944-02 (Box 2, Folder 1-9)
- Correspondence, 1944-02-1944-12 (Box 3, Folder 1-8)
- Correspondence, 1945-01-1945-07 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
- Correspondence from Esther Frank to David Smith, 1943-1945 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Cleveland Industrial Union Council, 1941-1944 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Medical Committee for Human Rights, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Correspondence to Esther Frank, 1943-1945 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Newspapers Announcing the End of WWII, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Stuyvestant Town Eviction 1, 1950-1952 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Stuyvestant Town Eviction 2, 1950-1952 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- By-laws of Organization, Undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
- American Jewish Conference, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Relocation Study, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Letters in Support, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Press Releases, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Proposed Legislation, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Contacts List, Undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Committee Members, Undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Bills for Committee, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Newspaper Articles, 1950-1952 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Legal Papers, 1949-1951 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Photocopied Newspaper Articles, 1950-2006 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Dorsey v. Stuyvestant, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Stuyvestant Special Bulletins, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Tenants' Committee Booklets and Media, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Tenants' Committee Letters, 1949-1951 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Tenants' Committee Memoranda, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Tenants' Committee Notices, 1950-1952 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Petitions, 1950-1952 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Stuyvestant Town Article, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Leaflets, 1949-1952 (Box 5, Folder 23)